<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-21T16:43:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">VRCC</title><subtitle>App marketing template for Jekyll.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Good Fire vs. Bad Fire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/good-fire-vs-bad-fire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Good Fire vs. Bad Fire" /><published>2020-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/good-fire-vs--bad-fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/good-fire-vs-bad-fire/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;vance-russell-and-eric-holst-explain-why-it-is-necessary-to-distinguish-between-good-fire-and-bad-fire&quot;&gt;Vance Russell and Eric Holst explain why it is necessary to distinguish between good fire and bad fire.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climate crisis continues to unfold with massive wildfires in Australia in 2019/20 and multiple tragic wildlfires in California during 2018. The largest (Mendocino Complex, 1850 square kilometers / 700 square miles) and deadliest (Camp, 85 deaths) wildfires in California history took place in 2018. Perhaps it’s a sad commentary on the human psyche that it took disasters of this magnitude to mobilize action against such threats to lives, infrastructure and wild nature. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fire.ca.gov/grants/forest-health-grants/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;More than $1 billion will now be invested&lt;/a&gt; in California over the next five years, with multiple efforts to develop and implement wildfire mitigation projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase in funding is surely good to see, but it raises a series of pertinent questions. Will these efforts really accomplish their objective? Are there enough projects in the pipeline, and does California have the capacity to carry them out? How can an evidence base be built to prove that funding is really reducing the size and detrimental effect of forest fires on Californian residents and biodiversity? To answer these questions, we need to analyse wildfire behavior, mitigation and response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/photo2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;512&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad fire vs. good fire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When their consequences are looked at objectively, wildfires can be broadly classified as “good” or “bad”. Examining some real-life examples of Californian fires can help us tease the two apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sustainable forests of the Sierra Nevada are typically biodiverse and heterogeneous, resilient to wildfire, climate change and disease (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/psw/publications/documents/psw_gtr220/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;North, et al., 2009&lt;/a&gt;). The rural communities based here are vibrant, demographically stable and economically self-sufficient, with revenue streams that go beyond tourism and logging as shown in the Venn diagram below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/graphic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;611&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camp and Mendocino Complex fires of 2018, which both consumed extensive areas of Sierra Nevada forest, neatly illustrate the varying impact that wildfire can have on people, property and biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessing impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in November 2018, the Camp Fire was fueled by a bumper crop of dry grass generated by the preceding wet winter and scorching summer. Late in autumn during an unusual wind event and sparked by faulty Pacific Gas &amp;amp; Electric equipment, it quickly grew into a conflagration that swept into the town of Paradise, creating a firestorm reminiscent of those caused by the bombing of German cities during World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire eventually ravaged over 600 square kilometers (230 square miles) of land, destroyed nearly 19,000 structures, and tragically caused the deaths of 85 Paradise residents, many of whom were senior citizens and couldn’t leave the town in time. As the deadliest wildfire in California history, this was clearly a “bad” fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, the Mendocino Complex Fire, which burned from July through to November, 2018 ravaged around 1,850 square kilometers (700 square miles) of forest. However, it “only” destroyed 280 buildings—half of which were residential—and caused the death of one firefighter. In fact, Lake County, where much of the fire burned, has endured eight fires in the past three years, affecting half the county’s area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a single death is clearly a tragedy and loss of infrastructure is always costly, some would consider other outcomes of the Mendocino fire to have been a success. Forage for cattle was exceptionally good during 2019, while wildflowers, chaparral species (especially those that are serotinous, e.g., seed release dependent on exposure to fire or other environmental triggers) and wildlife are all thriving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the ferocity and extent with which they burned, it is almost impossible to speculate what could have prevented both the Camp and Mendocino Complex fires from starting or spreading. However, the Mendocino fire may have done more good than bad, revitalizing brush and chaparral that had not burned in years due to fire suppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Letting it burn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An examination of the Rim Fire of 2014 is also instructive in terms of the good fire vs. bad fire debate. The Rim Fire burned fast and furious in the Sierra Nevada’s Stanislaus National Forest, where fires had been suppressed for years. But when it approached the border of Yosemite National Park, where the park service has long practiced controlled burning and intentionally allowed less serious wildfires to burn, the fire dropped from the forest crown to the floor and did far less damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years it was incredibly rare to simply let wildfires burn—only 0.4% of all ignitions in the United States between 1998 and 2008 were allowed to burn without intervention. In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/09/27/649649316/fire-ecologists-say-more-fires-should-be-left-to-burn-so-why-arent-they?t=1563200133566&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;National Public Radio article&lt;/a&gt;, a district ranger in the Sierra National Forest recounts letting the Lions Fire (June-July 2018) burn because it was located away from property and was in an area populated with dead (i.e., highly flammable) trees. While the fire eventually had to be suppressed due to high winds, letting it burn long without control lowered the risk of a more serious fire in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting wildfires burn is slowly starting to become more common practice. The figure below outlines a framework where fires of low to medium intensity occurring in wilderness and wildland urban interface (WUI) are allowed to burn. The prescribed fire (Rx) continuum depicted in the same figure shows where more prescribed fire and thinning should be applied to reduce the risk of dangerous fires close to urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/graphic-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;951&quot; height=&quot;709&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back to the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 1920 and 1950, about 40,000-200,000 square kilometres (15,000 and 77,000 square miles) of forest was allowed to burn in the United States every year. Yet by the 1950s, annual burning was reduced to less than 8,000 square kilometres (3,000 square miles) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://islandpress.org/books/firestorm&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Struzik, 2019&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In California, before fire suppression was widely practiced, around 15,500 square kilometers (6,000 square miles) of forest burned every year. This is almost double the amount of forest that burned in the state in 2018, which was a bad year for fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these historic Californian wildfires were low intensity, low impact fires. Due to fire suppression and air quality restrictions, fires such as this rarely happen anymore. But they still provide an instructive lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By thinning out smaller diameter trees in prioritized WUI and fuel breaks, employing controlled burning over larger landscapes and letting remote fires burn, Californian forests could be restored to a far more fire resilient state, thereby avoiding many future tragedies. Yet only a Marshall plan-level of funding, planning, mobilization and monitoring will result in such effective threat mitigation. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><summary type="html">Vance Russell and Eric Holst explain why it is necessary to distinguish between good fire and bad fire.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/uploads/photo1.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Measuring conservation success in 5 minutes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/measuring-conservation-success-in-5-minutes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measuring conservation success in 5 minutes" /><published>2020-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/measuring-conservation-success-in-5-minutes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/measuring-conservation-success-in-5-minutes/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;conservation-monitoring-is-often-ignored-and-underfunded-but-it-shouldnt-be-vance-russell-explains-why&quot;&gt;Conservation monitoring is often ignored and underfunded, but it shouldn’t be. Vance Russell explains why.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A surprising question&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in a meeting, a colleague made a comment to me that was something to the effect of: “Can’t we just assume that all the work we’re doing is benefiting the environment?” He continued stating that many of the projects we’re doing have multiple benefits proven by research elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if this was true, ecological conditions are so variable across the many landscapes where we work that such generalities cannot be applied. Even if we do see benefits, are they actually quantified and scientifically defensible or are they just anecdotal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a simpler analogy from the business world: No successful business would ever assume they are making a profit if the literature said their business should be successful. A CEO would manage the company to maximize profits. The same corporate leader and their financial managers would be constantly checking the numbers to validate not just the profit margin, but to also determine whether or not there were additional strategies to cut costs, increase sales and increase profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem with assumptions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet in the conservation world we often conduct business without checking the books. We make the assumption that if we plant trees, or get volunteers out in nature or restore a stream, those activities will immediately lead to good things. Even worse, we invest in fundraising and financial systems, sometimes costing $10’s to 100’s of thousands, but often skimp on developing scientifically sound monitoring, reporting and communications systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/monitoring-blog-photo1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;790&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservation education is a classic example for making assumptions about outcomes. For years, conservation educators assumed that bringing children, adults and other volunteers to help plant trees, remove invasive weeds, or add gravel to a stream was a good thing. Of course they had the actual projects to show for the work and the volunteers or students that helped on the projects enjoyed the work. But no one really asked key questions around the impact of environmental education on the participants. Did outdoor education lead to a cadre of people supporting conservation? Did the kids later become environmental professionals and/or supportive of environmental causes? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one had any data to show what the outcomes of outdoor education was on the participants. Gradually donor interests moved away from conservation education and without data to show the benefits, nonprofits, especially those that specialized in bringing volunteers to projects, struggled to bring their donors back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, several organizations decided to start gathering this type of data. Again, those in the business world might think: “What would you do without financial and marketing data?” And they’d probably answer: “You would likely fail.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, the Center for Land-Based Learning (Woodland, California) started tracking students who participated in their restoration field days with farmers and ranchers in a program known as SLEWS (Student Landowner Education and Watershed Stewardship). They not just tracked SLEWS alumni following the field days, but also as they moved into college and to careers. Some validating results came from the study carried out surveying students over 14 years of participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, 51 percent of surveyed participants said SLEWS affected their higher education and career path. SLEWS sparked an interest in pursuing multiple agricultural and environmental career paths. One student said “SLEWS made me want to get into ecology and forestry and help out the environment…it cemented that idea of what I wanted to do in the future.” More broadly speaking 89 percent of survey respondents said SLEWS helped them gain experience in something they would not other had the opportunity to do: “Being able to leave Oak Park or South Sac…was an eye opening experience…if it wasn’t for SLEWS I wouldn’t have gone to college and majored in biology.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/photo2-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another far-reaching example was Integrated Conservation and Development Projects that multiple conservation organizations invested in starting in the 1980s. Integrated Conservation and Development Projects proponents assumed that if community development projects near protected areas (national parks, forests, reserves) are funded and developed, they would lead to less deforestation, poaching and general degradation faced by nearby protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deforestation and “empty forests” after local communities hunted many species to local extinction was a growing problem at the time, largely due to many parks being gazetted without proper management plans, staffing and funding to develop the parks. They were sometimes known as paper parks. The development projects were typically agricultural extension projects, often top-down and expert-driven, that introduced “better” or more intensive ways to farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservationists made two massive assumptions: 1) that the agricultural intensification or community development programs would work—not guaranteed given the rate of failure of development projects in South and Central America; and 2) agricultural intensification would lead to less forest clearing since increased production would allow farms to continue cultivating the same pieces of land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not until the late 1990s did anyone ask if or how the projects were successful in and of themselves, but more importantly, no one examined the assumption that community development led to reduced threats to forests either. While at the Biodiversity Support Program, I worked with a team of researchers that examined whether or assumptions one and two were actually valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected quantitative and qualitative data on land use, crops yields, project information and interviews/surveys of community members in the field at two Integrated Conservation and Development Project projects in Mexico (El Ocote Biosphere Reserve) and Guatemala (Sierra de las Minas National Park). We found that the project’s focus on farmer-to-farmer extension increased yields. Paradoxically in Guatemala, where more land was available, increased yields sometimes led to increased land clearing. This land tenure phenomenon is known as the poverty paradox and typically happens when increased yields increase family income which allows them to afford to clear and till more land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At both sites, participation in sustainable agriculture programs generally led to more environmental consciousness, and participating farmers burned the forest less. So the programs helped to reduce the use of fire and therefore reduced the incidence of deforestation. When land tenure was more secure, however, farmers also tended to clear less. So the general assumption of Integrated Conservation and Development Projects in this case was true and false and depended on multiple factors. More details on the study can be found in the publication &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cifor.org/library/1028/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Maximum Yield?: Sustainable Agriculture as a Tool for Conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fosonline.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/Maximum-Yield.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/photo3-attribute-to-luc-viatour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to do&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many approaches to testing that are relatively easy to implement. The World Wildlife Fund has multiple documents on developing conceptual models and building monitoring into everyday conservation available online. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.conservationmeasures.org/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;conservation measures partnership&lt;/a&gt; is another great resource. Here are several ideas to get you started: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptual models&lt;/strong&gt;. Even writing down the assumptions you’re making is better than nothing. Creating models that help everyone involved in a project visualize how the system works is critical for asking assumptions about cause and effect in conservation and restoration projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volunteers&lt;/strong&gt;. Measuring outcomes costs money and often grants only include funding for implementation, not measurement. Additionally, it can also be complicated to measure results with so many confounding factors involved, and we are still learning a lot about how ecosystems work. Here are some ways to measure results without additional funding: Citizen science. Engage your local university. Incorporate measures of success into project funding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reporting&lt;/strong&gt;. Reporting back to donors, social media and a wider audience on what you learned is a valuable exercise. Reporting doesn’t have to be published in a peer-reviewed journal, but could just be a blog, a newsletter article or a presentation at a conference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;. Work with multiple NGOs doing similar work to share resources, results and measure success at larger scales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As conservationists we can no longer afford to assume that all the work we do is beneficial to local ecosystems and the planet. While measuring success can be complicated or costly, it is critical work to maximize the return on investment. Conservation practitioners owe that to donors the ecosystems they are trying to save. Return is more easily measured in the business world, but the more it is done in the conservation arena, the more likely projects will attain the high standards we expect for preserving the biodiversity of life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><summary type="html">Conservation monitoring is often ignored and underfunded, but it shouldn’t be. Vance Russell explains why.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/uploads/photo3-attribute-to-luc-viatour.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tech4Wildlife - Open source, collaborative and revolutionary</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/tech4wildlife-open-source-collaborative-and-revolutionary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tech4Wildlife - Open source, collaborative and revolutionary" /><published>2020-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/tech4wildlife---open-source-collaborative-and-revolutionary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/tech4wildlife-open-source-collaborative-and-revolutionary/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;originally-published-on-thecieem-website-this-article-has-been-updated-and-expanded&quot;&gt;Originally published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cieem.net/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;CIEEM website&lt;/a&gt;, this article has been updated and expanded.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human race has never been more connected through technology than it is now. Technology, in its many guises, has enhanced the life of virtually every global citizen—through energy, healthcare, food, transport and jobs. We dream of living longer, of understanding the myriad complexities of time and matter, of colonizing the Solar System and beyond (by the way, for all you planetary colonization fans, there’s no trout on mars!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those involved in ecology and environmental management, the whirlwind pace of technological development is understandably exciting. New tools and techniques are allowing practitioners across the globe to perform more effectively, more cooperatively, at lower costs and greater scale as they tackle pressing and complex problems such as climate change and biodiversity decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the growing mobility, affordability and connectivity of tools for data collection and analysis—from DNA sequencers and camera traps to remote sensing and artificial intelligence—is revolutionizing how we research, monitor and restore our natural environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developments in areas such as virtual reality, the internet of things and blockchain suggest further radical change. Remote sensing and visual representation technologies are evolving rapidly through increasingly sophisticated satellites and drones, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.movebank.org/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Movebank &lt;/a&gt;(an online animal tracking database) posting dramatic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TG4eCWkdyQY&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; depicting global animal movement, &lt;a href=&quot;http://planet.com/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;planet.com&lt;/a&gt; flying the earth thousands of times daily with their football size satellites and infrared cameras finding mammals in canopies far easier than the human eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/photo2-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1400&quot; height=&quot;550&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet for all its burgeoning potential, technology also presents ecologists with a host of challenges. As it gives rise to new disciplines that we need to shape, apply and master, we are all learning rapidly. This learning process encompasses evolving scientific fields such as drone and soundscape ecology and groundbreaking techniques such as eDNA. And in an era of unprecedented access to biodiversity and conservation data, it also involves the development of decision support tools that can help others process information and knowledge in more informative, standardized ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenges also abound in the practical application of technology. Camera traps, although arguably invaluable for conservation science and management, are making wilderness less wild and may change animal behavior, while drones have been proven to increase animal stress (&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0178448&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Pazmany, 2018&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/photo3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forwards, new principles may need to be put in practice to help govern, regulate and provide ethical guidance for the use of conservation technology. Isaac Asimov’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auburn.edu/~vestmon/robotics.html&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Three Laws of Robotics&lt;/a&gt; may no longer seem so far fetched, particularly with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/robots/a22839698/lionfish-hunting-robot/&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;robots &lt;/a&gt;already combing Caribbean reefs to remove lionfish or futuristic proposals for autonomous robots that safeguard wilderness areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maximize its effectiveness, conservation technology needs to be as collaborative, transparent and open source as possible. Tech start-ups, policy makers, NGOs, big business, the finance sector, local communities and environmental consultancies all need to come together to build a conservation technology community that identifies challenges and develops and deploys innovative solutions as rapidly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><summary type="html">Originally published on the CIEEM website, this article has been updated and expanded.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/uploads/photo1-1.jpg" /></entry></feed>